(ball bouncing)
- [Bankole Alade]
Schooling was never a goal,
like I never thought of schooling
as being a way to get
a better life for me,
I thought if I didn't
make it in basketball,
I wouldn't make it at all.
(crowd cheering)
[Game Audio]
(light music)
(shoe squeaking)
- I started playing
basketball at eight years old.
I was really really bad
my first couple years
I never played basketball before
My dad never played basketball before
and I remember watching Kobe Bryant
play basketball and I was like,
"Wow I didn't know you
could really do that stuff."
I'd never seen anyone
do anything like that.
So after that, I actually fell in love
with the game a lot more.
I spent hours and hours practicing
and ever since then, I've
been playing competitively.
- [Coach] I remember it was
in the other gym and you said,
"Coach O, If I steal, if I make
this one from center court,
you gotta play me one
on one," and he made it.
So we had to play one on one.
- I remember I won though.
- [Coach O'Rourk] Yeah you won.
- [Coach O'Rourk] My assistant coach,
he was at the nationals, and
Banky was on Team Alberta
and we were searching
for a particular need
which was rebounding and athletic forward.
Conrad had texted me right away
when he was out there after watching
Alberta and Banky play and Banky actually
lead the nationals in
rebounding that summer.
I mean we have a motto, we try and say,
"recruit character, teach skill."
and he's definitely a character kid
right from the beginning.
(door opening and shutting)
- [Bankole Alade] Early
on I didn't do well.
I was playing like zero minutes.
I was probably playing like
two minutes every second game.
At the same time, I was
doing terrible at school.
I remember at the end
of my first semester,
I actually almost got
kicked out of university
for having a super low average.
I'm just saying to myself, "This is old."
Why, why am I, why am
I doing all this for.
This doesn't make any sense.
(inspirational music)
- [Coach O'Rourk] Well he struggled,
he struggled academically and
he struggled with basketball.
- I even told one of
my friends before end,
I told him, "I'm about to talk to Chris,
I'm about to quit the basketball team
and I'm about to drop out of school."
- [Coach O'Rourk] I remember
Conrad and I sitting down
with him and saying "You
know it's your first year
it's a transition."
- He said, "Banky, we see
you have a lot of potential
inside of you." And he
tried to make me question
if I really had done everything possible.
You're not training all the time.
You're not going to workouts all the time.
Like you're not doing
everything you need to,
to be successful and that's something
I never really thought about.
I feel like I, especially early on,
it was more me not being good enough.
And less of me not working hard enough.
(ball bouncing)
- [Coach O'Rourk] Let's
do a rescreen roll.
Come and we'll rescreen.
- [Bankole Alade] That summer,
I was training every day
I lifted every day. I
feel like I noticed myself
getting better from a
basketball standpoint.
But if it is possible for me
to get better at basketball
by working harder, why
isn't it possible for me
to improve the rest of my
life by working a bit harder.
- [Coach O'Rourk] So the
student athlete mentor program,
there's all kinds of resources there.
How to write papers,
study habits, there's just
a whole gambit of things they can access.
And Banky was in that,
I think he just felt
his confidence grow.
- Personally, I did not
like school whatsoever.
But taking marketing was
such a different rope
than any of the other classes I've taken.
They weren't grading me on
how much I could remember,
or how much I studied before hand.
They graded me on more of a how well
I'm able to convey thoughts of
what I'm thinking in my head.
Allow me to use a
different side of my brain
that I wasn't used to that I
actually enjoyed a lot more.
This one good I mean I'm
doing digital strategy.
So it's a little bit different
than... (faded talking)
- [Dr. Rodenburg] I think
that he found his passion.
I think he found his confidence.
I think he found his voice.
And I think he realized he
can contribute in some way.
- Head companies who have,
who may have ulterior motives
The University of Guelph
has a lot of resources
to help students do good in school.
I would tell every single student,
if you want to do well on essays,
go to the writing services
at the learning center
because they're there to help,
and you will do better guaranteed.
JC was the first club
that I joined at Guelph.
The first step of actually
joining a student club
was something I never
thought that I would do ever.
It helped me grow a lot as a person.
And being in a club, you
realize how important
these things really are
to maximizing your success
at the university, but one of
the things I began to realize
is that no black students
would ever attend these events.
(inspirational music)
- It's gonna be an exciting journey.
This is the first time
we're doing it obviously
(several students talking)
- [Mikyas Tessema] I wanted
to be a part of a organization
that endorsed the networking between
black students and young professionals.
And as soon as I saw Banky's post,
I thought this was the
best place for me to have
that team feeling at U of G.
- [Bankole Alade] There
was such a big divide
and black students were missing out.
And we felt that we could
easily take down these barriers
that they see and hopefully
get them to capitalize
on these amazing opportunities
that the university has.
- [Mikyas Tessema] The
Guelph Black Professionals
has shown me how to be a better leader,
you're only as strong
as your weakest link,
so, as long as everyone is involved
and actively participating
the whole team will be successful.
- Having this organization not only helps
black students in our community,
it helps everybody else think differently
about the community.
Everything that you're
doing is influencing
and affecting people so
positively, it's so amazing.
I am so proud to know you.
- [Bankole Alade] Thank you.
- Yeah I mean you are just incredible.
I think what happens is we
come with voices in our head
that have been told to us our whole lives,
and I see for Banky someone
that might have been
telling himself wrong
things about who he was.
And I think as an institution
and as an instructor
our opportunities help
them find those voices,
the real voices, who they really are.
- [Bankole Alade] You can find
passion in any university.
I think if anyone looked
at me in first year,
I don't think anyone
really would have said,
"you could be going to do your Master's."
I couldn't do it. I didn't
think I could do it.
I don't have the grades to do this.
But now to be where I am now,
I have all these possibilities
and all these opportunities.
And it's just so amazing to think about.
(inspirational music)