(gentle inspirational music)
- [Narrator] Our planet
faces a major problem,
one of its biggest ever, in fact,
and we need to solve it now.
We must find efficient, effective,
and sustainable ways to
feed our growing population,
all while protecting the environment.
At the University of Guelph,
we have a 150-year legacy in agrifood,
and we are committed to
innovation and research
for years to come.
We have the capacity to bring together
the people and resources needed
to pioneer Canada's next
agricultural revolution,
and to go grow this
country's food economy.
Now, with a game-changing investment
from the Canada First
Research Excellence Fund,
we are ready to lead
in meeting this food security challenge.
That's food FROM thought.
From Canada's food university,
the University of Guelph.