- Change happens at a community level.
Small people put in small efforts
and those efforts add up to something big.
I knew it was going to be a challenge
to set something up like this,
but sometimes it is the
nitty-gritty, tiny little details
that are going to make the difference.
(somber music)
I was in Creelman in first year
and I just kind of asked out of curiosity.
I was like, "Are the
leftovers kind of repurposed
or are they donated?"
- We had been donating food at that time
on a relatively small scale.
Operations in commercial
kitchens and Public Health rules
don't make donating food very easy.
(somber music)
- It's very easy for people to say, "No."
It's not just, "You're in MealCare. Great.
We divert food.
It's so fun. It's so easy."
There are some people that maybe
don't think it's going to work initially,
or sometimes there are
just logistical challenge.
- Often we do have to hear, "No,"
and it's not really because certain donors
don't want to work with us.
It's just because there
are a lot of details
that we need to work out.
And for that reason,
we do hear, "No," a lot
but we continue to persevere
until we can make some
kind of partnership.
- [Interviewer] So who said, "Yes"?
- Well, one of our first big
yeses was from Chef Vijay,
and he was one of our
really great supporters.
- When Kiana and David approached
us with the MealCare idea,
it was a no-brainer for us.
The plan and the enthusiasm
that Kiana and David came up with
was something that we had not seen before.
- [David] After our first
yes, we were able to continue
to foster that relationship
and put ourselves
in a position where we
could expand our impact.
- The very first time that
I heard about MealCare
was actually in this room.
David and Kiana went up to the
front of the entire lecture,
which was over 400 students,
and gave the most inspiring
speech that I've ever heard
about how passionate they are
to reduce student security.
(gentle music)
- Guelph is a food school.
There's such a focus
on sustainability here.
And so that's why I really
feel like MealCare just fits.
- It is the younger
generation who have solutions
for many of the problems today.
And the university has to
support them to succeed.
- We're so grateful.
We've had so much help along the way.
And our team of volunteers
has really made the world of difference.
- Without them, we wouldn't
have actually been able to grow
to actually be in a position
where we could impact more change.
- [Students] Hi.
- [Woman] Hi.
- [Kiana] How are you?
Whenever I do a donation for MealCare,
it just makes me feel empowered.
Something about seeing the physical food
being taken off of the car
and put somewhere where you
know that it's going to be used,
it's really, I think it's really cool.
Yeah, it's a really special feeling.
- I'm originally from India
and I've seen, firsthand, the
poverty and food insecurity
that affects millions of people.
Canada is one of the wealthiest
countries in the world
and stats have, time and again, shown
that we waste 1/3 of all
the food that is produced.
So it falls upon all of us,
personally and professionally,
to take ownership of this problem,
which really can be solved.
- Different groupings of food.
We have beverages, we have
fresh foods we have...
In the homeless population,
there's also a deficit in terms of feeling
that they're cared for.
In official discussion
about homeless people,
we're talking about people
with no fixed address, right?
And a fixed address is not actually
going to solve that problem.
It's really important for people
that are living insecurely,
that they have a sense of home
and home begins when there's community
and when there's caring.
The MealCare meals, as
they started coming in,
we couldn't believe the quality.
When people know that they're
going to be able to get
not just any food but
really good quality food,
nice variety,
yeah, it just tells you
that you're worth something,
you're worthwhile.
(gentle music)
- Food security, if you think
of the actual definition
is like, safe, affordable, accessible,
culturally appropriate,
and just some of the things
we're able to donate,
like we have vegetarian
options and gluten free,
and a lot of our meals are halal.
- It's not food waste or leftover,
it's good food, nutritious food
that can really make a
difference in someone's life.
Since our inception at MealCare Guelph,
we have donated 14,163 pounds of food.
- Wow, that's impressive.
- Go to your calculator.
Let's see.
14,000 pounds divided by 365:
38.35.
38 and 1/3 years of free lunches,
if your lunch weighs one pound.
That's so much food.
I think it's really cool.
The very first donation Dave and I did
was just the two of us,
wheeling a little wheelbarrow
of food in the freezing cold.
- For our first couple of donations,
it wasn't a lot of food, right?
But when you put it into perspective,
even a couple of pounds,
that can feed so many people
who can really depend on it.
And it was just such an amazing feeling.
- I feel like I'm really
making a difference
in someone's life.
And it just makes me feel proud to be
a University of Guelph student.
- Even though it seems like food waste
is a very daunting global issue,
small, proactive, continued change
is really going to make a
difference in the long run.
It is challenging and it's
never going to be easy
but the reward is so worth it
if you're willing to really
fight for our message
and what we believe in.
(gentle music)