At the University of Guelph, sustainability is an expression of
our mission to Improve Life. For us, sustainability is about
stewarding our valued resources – our people, our campus and
our planet – in order to meet the needs of the present, without
compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own
needs. At U of G, sustainability truly is a part of our shared story.
On our physical campus, promoting sustainability means
everything from reducing greenhouse gas emissions to
building a circular food system. It is also about using the University
as a living laboratory to incubate the big, bold and bright ideas that
generate new knowledge to improve life locally, and around
the world.
Our faculty are at the forefront of finding innovative solutions to the
most pressing issues of our time. U of G has 250 faculty engaged
in sustainability-related research. Our students can also enroll in
over 500 sustainability-focused courses.
Through grassroots mobilization, community engagement,
research and experiential learning, our students are at the
forefront leading change both on and off campus. Their work has
inspired and motivated changes that advance sustainability at the
University, in local communities and internationally.
Because at the University of Guelph, sustainability is part of
who we are – for all who choose to study here, explore here,
teach here and work here, sustainability is part of
our shared story.